{"tossups": [{"question": "This country attempted to recreate a Six Day War strategy by launching Operation Chengiz Khan, disabling a rival\u2019s air force in retaliation for their support of Mukti Bahini. Under Yahya Khan, this country launched Operation Searchlight to suppress the Awami League, a nationalist movement in a breakaway state. This country fought the Kargil War and frequently contests the region of Kashmir with its eastern neighbor. Bangladesh gained its independence from, for ten points, what northwestern neighbor of India?", "answer": "Islamic Republic of<b> Pakistan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "One of which was altered by Rosemary Woods and includes a mysterious 18-and-a-half minute gap. For ten points, name this type of document that was used as audio evidence in the Watergate scandal.", "answer": "Richard<b> Nixon</b>\u2019s<b> White House tape</b> recordings (accept<b> Watergate tape</b> recordings before\u201cWatergate\u201d is mentioned; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In retirement, this man announced a series of articles limiting entertainment expenses and who can ride on palanquins, the \u201cLaws of the Military Houses.\u201d Late in life, this man lived in Sunpu Castle, where he had been held hostage as a child. This man abdicated the throne in favor of his son Hidetada [hi-day-tah-da]. This man\u2019s victory at Osaka Castle brought an end to the rival Toyotomi clan. For ten points, name this warlord who established the last shogunate of Japan.", "answer": "<b> Tokugawa</b> Ieyasu", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A letter from Cicero describes this event as a \u201csuperb banquet\u201d that he wished he had been a part of; that letter was written to Trebonius, who did take part. Servilius Casca almost revealed the timing of this event, which was later avenged at the Battle of Philippi. Calpurnia failed to deter the target of this event from appearing before the Senate. For ten points, name this event carried out on the Ides of March, 44 BC by Brutus, Cassius, and other conspirators against the dicatator of Rome.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> (or<b> killing</b>,<b> stabbing</b>, etc.) of (Gaius)<b> Julius Caesar</b> (prompt on partial answers, like \u201cassassination of Caesar\u201d)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A document calling for the creation of this legislative body was issued by a member of the House of Commons named Edwin Sandys. The first session of this body was presided over by George Yeardley. The cities of Henricus and Hundred Plantation were among those represented in this body. Vetoes could be issued by the governor overseeing this body, which also ceded power to its colony\u2019s namesake company. For ten points, name this elected assembly established in 1619 in the Colony of Virginia.", "answer": "<b> House of Burgesses</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A painting in the tomb of Puimre recorded one of these animals called \u201cNedjem,\u201d or \u201csweet,\u201d and the tomb painting \u201cFowling in the Marshes\u201d shows one of these animals biting the wing of a bird. Herodotus described people shaving their eyebrows in mourning for these creatures, eighty thousand of which were found in Beni Hassan, and many of whom were entombed at Bubastis. Bast had the head of, for ten points, what domestic mammal whose names included mau and mju [mah-oo and \u201cmew\u201d] in ancient Egypt, where they were revered?", "answer": "domestic<b> cat</b> (accept common nicknames, like<b> kitty</b>-cat or<b> puss</b>y-cat,<b> feline</b>, etc.; accept <b>felis</b> (silvestris)<b> catus</b>) (9) Directly before he founded the<em> New York Tribune</em>, Horace Greeley published a newspaper of this name. Bob Dole\u2019s 1996 presidential campaign controversially returned a $1,000 Republican donation from a group with this name; that group sued the U.S. in 2010 against the military\u2019s \u201cDon\u2019t Ask, Don\u2019t Tell\u201dpolicy. A group of Republicans who advocate for LGBT rights is named after, for ten points, what type of frontier house, one of which served as Abraham Lincoln\u2019s birthplace? ANSWER:<b> log cabin</b>s (accept<b> Log Cabin</b> Republicans; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This agreement amended the ruling<em> Inter caetera</em>. Henry Harrisse claims that Jaime Ferrer devised the earliest suggested answer to the central question of this agreement. This agreement, which was authenticated in the city of Setubal, was agreed to a year after the Bulls of Donation were issued by Pope Alexander I. Pedro Cabral\u2019s discovery of Brazil contributed to a boundary passing through South America in, for ten points, what 1494 agreement that established a meridian dividing New World holdings between Spain and Portugal?", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Tordesillas</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Late in life, this woman may have taken on the name Porivo, as Charles Eastman discovered while trying to locate her remains. Despite being kidnapped by the Hidatsa people, this woman was able to reunite with her brother Cameahwait. This woman, who helped navigate obstacles like Bozeman Pass, was married to Toussaint Charbonneau; the couple was recruited at Fort Mandan to join the Corps of Discovery. For ten points, name this Shoshone woman who accompanied Lewis and Clark on their expedition.", "answer": "<b> Sacagawea</b> (accept<b> Sakakawea</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "John F. Hylan defeated a holder of this position who ran on a platform of universal military training; that man, John Purroy Mitchel, died after falling from a plane. Another holder of this position employed a man who used the CompStat program in his attempts to crack down on petty crime as an application of the \u201cbroken windows\u201d theory. Bill Bratton served as police commissioner under Rudy Giuliani, who held this position during 9/11. For ten points, name this political office currently held by Bill de Blasio?", "answer": "<b> Mayor</b> of<b> New York</b> City (or<b> mayor of NY</b>C; prompt on partial answers, like \u201cleader of New York\u201d or \u201cmayor\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This scientist proved that diamonds are produced of carbon by observing the production of carbon dioxide from a diamond exposed to sunlight. This man, who discovered that respiration is actually a combustion reaction, is considered to have written the first chemistry textbook, his<em> Elementary Treatise</em> <em>on Chemistry</em>; in that book, this man provided names for oxygen and hydrogen. The law of conservation of mass was discovered by, for ten points, what \u201cfather of modern chemistry,\u201d a Frenchman who was guillotined in 1794?", "answer": "Antoine<b> Lavoisier</b>", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {}, {"question": "This country was the site of the first usage of jamming chaff, where planes used \u201cwindow\u201d tinfoil strips to block radar during Operation Gomorrah. This country was the target of Operation Chastise, where Barnes Wallis developed an explosive that could jump on water to strike the Eder valley. Arthur Harris was accused of committing an \u201cact of terror\u201d by Winston Churchill after his planes set off a firestorm that killed 25,000 in this country\u2019s region of Saxony. For ten points, name this country where Dresden was bombed during World War II.", "answer": "Nazi<b> Germany</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "An investigation at this location found that a design of Babcock and Wilcox had failed eleven times before it did so here. Roger Levin was among the authors of a medical article claiming that an event at this site did not cause increased incidence of thyroid cancer in Dauphin County. This location, named for its distance from the city of Middletown, lies on the Susquehanna River. A 1979 incident at this location was caused by a stuck valve at reactor 2. For ten points, name this American nuclear plant that experienced a partial meltdown.", "answer": "<b> Three Mile Island</b> Nuclear Generating Station (accept descriptive answers of a (nuclear) power plant at<b> Three Mile Island</b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "<b>During this period, journalist Anthony Grey was imprisoned when the British legation was attacked in response to the suppression of leftist protests. A government based on</b> <b>the Paris Commune was founded during this period as part of the (+)</b> <b>\u201cJanuary Storm.\u201d</b> <b>The man who inspired this period later described it as \u201c70 percent achievements and 30 percent mistakes.\u201d The (*)</b> \u201cFour Olds\u201d were attacked during this period by student groups called the Red Guards. For ten points, name this period of unrest from 1966 to 1976 that targeted\u201ccounter-revolutionaries\u201d in China.", "answer": "Great Proletarian<b> Cultural Revolution</b> [or Wuchanjieji<b> Wenhua Dageming</b> or<b> Wenge</b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A member of this family lost his re-election campaign as Governor of Rhode Island after he wiretapped a detective agency he had hired to investigate election fraud. During the sinking of the</b><em><b> Lusitania</b></em><b>, a member of this family gave his (+) life vest to an infant despite the fact that he couldn\u2019t swim. Holland McTyeire convinced a member of this family to fund a university. This family built Grand Central (*) </b> Station to bolster one of its businesses. TV journalist Anderson Cooper is a member of, for ten points, what American family whose patriarch, Cornelius, built a shipping empire?", "answer": "<b> Vanderbilt</b> family (accept William Henry<b> Vanderbilt</b> III; accept Alfred Gwynne<b> Vanderbilt </b>Sr; accept Cornelius<b> Vanderbilt</b>; do not accept Cooper)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Thousands of \u201ccasket girls\u201d emigrated to what is now this state, and their descendants are granted linguistic rights in this state\u2019s 1974 Constitution. People subject to the Great</b> <b>Upheaval migrated to this state under (+)</b> <b>Henri Peyroux de la Coudreni`ere [en-REE</b> <b>Henri Peyroux de la Coudreni`ere [en-REE</b> <b>pay-roo de la koo-dren-ee-air] after being forced out by British troops after the (*)</b> <b>pay-roo de la koo-dren-ee-air] after being forced out by British troops after the (*)</b> Seven Years War. The Acadians migrated to, for ten points, what US state with strong French traditions like the Napoleonic Code and celebrations of Mardi Gras in New Orleans?", "answer": "<b> Louisiana</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The long lasting effects of this event were studied in the 2006 TORCH report. The first responders to this event were formed into the \u201cliquidators\u201d and given medals of red drops of blood overlapped by (+) alpha and beta particles. A facility in Forsmark, Sweden found evidence of this event the following day. This event created the (*)</b> Red Forest in a 30 kilometer exclusion zone around Pripyat. For ten points, name this 1986 disaster at a Soviet nuclear power plant.", "answer": "<b> Chernobyl</b> disaster (accept any additional information relating to a meltdown and/or explosion at the<b> Chernobyl</b> nuclear power plant) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>This queen is the subject of numerous Nicholas Hilliard miniatures. Thomas</b> <b>Phelippes uncovered a plot to assassinate this ruler by the Jesuit priest John Ballard. The Bond of Association was drafted under this queen to execute usurpers, including</b> <b>Sir (+)</b> <b>Francis Throckmorton. This ruler\u2019s \u201cspymaster,\u201d Francis Walsingham</b> <b>uncovered many plots to replace this monarch with (*)</b> Mary, Queen of Scots. This Tudor queen continued her father\u2019s break with the Church in Rome. For ten points, name this \u201cVirgin Queen\u201d of England. ANSWER:<b> Elizabeth I</b> (prompt on Elizabeth)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}